American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Series 3: New York Office Records, consists of records of staff, rosters, printed matter, photographs, personal papers, Association of Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, and miscellaneous records.
Records of staff, 1919-1950 and undated, include the office files of Executive Secretaries Roscoe Guersney, Meriwether Stuart, and Mary T. Williams; Librarian George K. Boyce; and Endowment Fund Campaign Secretaries Phillilps B. Robinson and Edgar I. Williams.
The rosters, 1895-1939 and undated, are printed forms completed by fellows and students, with occasional attachments (usually correspondence or photographs). Included are the rosters of the School of Fine Arts, School of Classical Studies, and School of Classical Studies Summer Sessions.
Printed matter, 1905-[1981?] and undated, has been classified as Academy produced and produced by others. Items produced by the Academy, 1905-[1981?], include general information including act of incorporation and by-laws, fundraising brochure, constitution, Directory of Fellows and Residents, histories of the institution, newsletter of the Director, and printed items relating to special events. Printed matter specifically relating to the School of Classical Studies includes annual announcements, the consolidation agreement, a directory, fellowship announcements and applications, lecture announcements, newsletters, and brochures about summer sessions. School of Fine Arts printed matter includes annual announcements, concert programs, exhibition checklists and catalogs, fellowship announcements and application forms, history, and newsletters.
Printed matter produced by others, 1905-1940 and undated, consists of three scrapbooks of news clippings and photographs compiled by the American Academy in Rome, extensive clipping files, and articles from miscellaneous publications. All of these items are about the American Academy in Rome, or by or about individuals associated with the institution. Also included is a poster for Leave Courses offered at the Academy for U. S. servicemen.
Photographs, 1891-1941 and undated, are organized into the categories of works of art, people, buildings, places, events, and miscellaneous. Works of art are by visiting students and fellows, Frank D. Millet, collaborative problems, Rome Prize Competitions in Architecture, Rome Prize Competitions in Landscape Architecture, and Prix de Rome Competition exhibitions. Photographs of people are both of individuals and groups; among the groups are summer school students and fellowship winners.
Buildings depicted are American Academy properties. Among them are the "New Building," including interior and exterior construction views; studios; and Villas Aurelia, Mirafiore, and Richardson. Also included is a group of photographs of Academy architecture students measuring buildings in Rome and Florence. Places pictured are views of the Academy property and surrounding areas.
Photographs of events include cricket games, Thanksgiving and Fourth of July dinners, Architectural League exhibition, and inauguration of the Manship Fountain. Miscellaneous photographs are of an architectural drawing for a proposed building.
Personal Papers, Memorabilia, and Ephemera, 1855-1923 an undated, were donated to the American Academy in Rome or otherwise left on its premises. None are official records generated by the institution. Included are: Ernest Lewis' photograph album/scrapbook; Allan Marquand's papers; Charles F. McKim's memorabilia, photographs, printed matter, and artifacts; Charles R. Morey's correspondence; and Elihu Vedder's Bible.
Records of the Association of the Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, 1913-1945 and undated), consist of a small number of scattered records including correspondence, fellows' war/government service information (compiled by Sidney Waugh), membership lists, and a newsletter.
Miscellaneous records, 1899-1926 and undated, are writings and architectural records. Writings consist of published and unpublished manuscript material about the American Academy in Rome and its history, and article by H. Siddons Mowbray advising on ornamentation, and text and illustrations for the Art and Archaeology issue on the Academy. Also included are fragments of unidentified letters. Architectural records [oversize] include property and floor plans of Villas Aurora, Chiaraviglio, Ferrari, and Ludovisi.
Series 4: Rome Office Records, consist of records of staff and personal papers. Records of staff, 1903-1947 and undated, include the office files of Directors H. Siddons Mowbray, George Breck, Jesse Benedict Carter, Gorham Phillips Stevens, James Monroe Hewlett, Chester H. Aldrich, Amey Aldrich [Acting Director, very briefly, perhaps unofficially], Charles R. Morey, and Laurance P. Roberts; and records of two members of the School of Fine Arts faculty, Frank P. Fairbanks, Professor of Fine Arts, and Felix Lamond, Professor of Music. Records of Carter, Stevens, Hewlett, and Aldrich appear to be fairly complete; records of early directors are sparse; those of Morey and Roberts appear to be missing significant portions; and those of Professors Fairbanks and Lamond consist of a few scattered items.
Also surviving are the personal papers of Director Gorham Phillips Stevens, 1912-1931 and undated), consisting of correspondence, financial records, and documentation of professional and charitable activities.
Arrangement
In general, the records of each officer and staff member are arranged alphabetically, with general correspondence preceding the alphabetical sequence; arrangement within each file is chronological, unless noted otherwise.
Records of the American Academy in Rome are organized into four major series. Each series is divided into several subseries, with the arrangement described in detail in the series descriptions.
Series 1: Predecessor Institutions, 1894-1913 (box 1; 0.88 linear ft.; Reels 5749-5750)
Series 2: Board of Trustees Records, 1897-1957, undated (boxes 1-17, 35, 37; 15.25 linear ft.; Reels 5750-5777)
Series 3: New York Office, 1855-circa 1981, undated (boxes 17-32, 36; 15 linear ft.; 5777-5795)
Series 4: Rome Office, 1903-1943, undated (boxes 32-34; 3 linear ft.; 5795-5800)
Related Material
Papers of a number of former fellows, trustees, and other individuals associated with the American Academy in Rome are among the holdings of the Archives of American Art.
Chaloner Prize Foundation records, 1915-1974 (microfilm reels 5664-5669) were received with the American Academy in Rome records. They have been arranged and described as a separate collection.
Valentine, Lucia and Alan Valentine. The American Academy in Rome, 1894-1969. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1973.
Appendices
Printed Matter, 1911-1964
The American Academy in Rome printed matter listed here was loaned for microfilming in 1965. The material was filmed on microfilm reels ITRO 2-3 and ITRO 11-13.
ITRO 2: Annual Reports, 1911/12-1915/16
ITRO 3: Annual Reports, 1916/17-1925/26
ITRO 11: Annual Reports, 1926/27-1932/33
ITR0 12: Annual Reports, 1934/35-1938/39, 1943-1951, 1951-1955, and 1955-1959
ITRO 13: Exhibition Catalogues- Annual Exhibitions, 1920-1939 and 19959-1963 [none published 1940-1958]
ITRO 13: Exhibition Catalogues-Special Exhibition Catalogue, Francis Scott Bradford, 1962
ITRO 13: Memorial Book of Annual Dinner, September 10, 1913 (includes texts of addresses by Dr. Edward Robinson, Royal Cortissoz, and Kenyon Cox)
ITRO 13: Recent Work of the School of Fine Arts, from Memoirs of the American Academy in Rome, vol. II, 1918 and vol. III, 1919
ITRO 13: History of the American Academy in Rome by C. Grant LaFarge 25th Anniversary, 1919
ITRO 13: American Academy in Rome at the World's Fair and the Golden Gate Exposition, 1939
ITRO 13: Newsletters, 1962-1964
Trustee Biographies
Chester H. Aldrich: architect; became a trustee of the American Academy in Rome in 1925; member of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts from 1927 until 1935, serving as its chairman from 1933 until 1935; in 1935 he was appointed director in Rome, where he remained until his death in 1940.
John Lambert Clarke Cadwalader: a New York attorney and former assistant secretary of state; an incorporator of the American Academy in Rome in 1905 and a life member; acted as an advisor for the incorporation process, was influential in endowment fundraising activities, and played an important role in the transfer of Villa Mirafiore; although trustee minutes indicate he attended some meetings, it is unclear whether Cadwalader was actually a trustee.
Gilmore D. Clarke: member of the Fine Arts Committee and chairman of the Special Committee on Villa Aurelia from 1944 to 1945.
James C. Egbert: professor of classics at Columbia University; served as the annual professor at the Rome School of Classical Studies in 1903/04; trustee of the American Academy in Rome from 1911 to 1945; became a member of the Committee on the School of Classical Studies in 1914 and served as its chairman between 1927 and 1940; during the 1930s he served on the Committee on Nominations, and from 1940 until 1944 was vice president of the academy.
Barry Faulkner: a fellow in painting at the American Academy in Rome from 1907 to 1910, and annual professor of fine arts from 1922 to 1923; for many years he was president of the Association of Alumni of the Academy; elected a trustee in 1930, he was appointed a member of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts that same year, and eventually became committee chairman; during World War II, he represented the American Academy in Rome on the Citizens Committee for the Army-Navy Triptych Project; awarded the American Academy in Rome medal for outstanding service in 1960.
Allan C. Johnson: professor of classics at Princeton University; trustee of the American Academy in Rome between 1929 and 1946; professor of classical studies during the academic year 1933/34, and for many years served as a member of the Committee on the School of Classical Studies, of which he was chairman from 1940 through 1945.
William M. Kendall: an architect and partner in the firm of McKim, Mead, and White, Kendall; was an incorporator, in 1905, and trustee of the American Academy in Rome from 1905 to 1941; served as a member of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts for many years.
C. Grant La Farge: a practicing architect who was active in the affairs of the American Institute of Architects; was elected a trustee of the American Academy in Rome in 1909, served on its executive committee, and was secretary to the board of trustees from 1912 to 1938.
Edward P. Mellon: architect and nephew of Andrew Mellon; became a trustee of the American Academy in Rome and served as acting secretary of the board from 1917 to 1918; served on the Endowment Committee, circa 1919-1923, first as its treasurer and later becoming its chairman.
Norton, Charles Dyer: a banker who was Assistant Secretary of the Treasury and private secretary to President Taft, from 1908 to 1911; elected a trustee of the American Academy in Rome in 1913; a member of the executive and finance committees, and served on the endowment committee from 1913 to 1917.
Charles A. Platt: became a trustee of the American Academy in Rome in 1919; an architect who joined the Committee on the School of Fine Arts in 1921 and was its chairman from 1927 until 1928; elected president in 1928, serving until his death in 1933.
John Russell Pope: first recipient of the Rome Prize in Architecture at the American School of Architecture in Rome from 1895 to 1897; a trustee of the American Academy in Rome from 1926 to 1933; served on the Committee on the School of Fine Arts, 1927-1938, and was president of the board from 1933 until his death in 1937.
Edward K. Rand: professor of Latin at Harvard University, Rand; elected a trustee of the American Academy in Rome in 1911; served for many years on the Committee on the School of Classical Studies, and during 1912/13 was a professor at the School of Classical Studies; resigned from the board in 1929 due to pressures of his Harvard workload, but many years later resumed his position as a trustee.
John C. Rolfe: professor of Latin at the University of Pennsylvania; taught at the American School of Classical Studies in Rome from 1907 to 1908, and at the American Academy in Rome from 1923 to 1924; served as a member of the Committee on the School of Classical Studies from 1921 to 1940; also served on the Committee on Publications for an undetermined period, and was its chairman during 1927.
James Kellum Smith: after holding the Stewardson Fellowship in Architecture of the University of Pennsylvania and the American Academy in Rome from 1920 to 1923, Smith joined the firm of McKim, Mead, and White; first elected a trustee in 1933, he was a member of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts and served as its chairman; president of the American Academy in Rome from 1937 until 1958 and in 1961 was awarded its medal for outstanding service.
S. Breck Trowbridge: an incorporator of the American Academy in Rome in 1905; became a trustee in 1906; chairman of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts from 1915 (and possibly earlier), served as vice president from 1917 to 1925, and was chairman of the endowment fund committee from 1919 to 1921.
Ferruccio Vitale: a landscape architect and trustee of the American Academy in Rome; instrumental in the founding of its landscape architecture department and establishing scholarships in landscape architecture; served on the Committee on the School of Fine Arts, 1921-1931 and was active in the Committee on Endowment's fundraising campaigns, 1914-1920.
John Quincy Adams Ward: Sculptor John Quincy Adams Ward was among the artist members of the first board of trustees of the American Academy in Rome in 1897.
Andrew F. West: professor of Latin at Princeton University, and later Dean of the Princeton Graduate School; chairman of the managing committee of the American School of Classical Studies in Athens; served as a trustee of the academy from 1911 to 1928, and from 1917 as chairman of the Advisory Committee on the School of Classical Studies.
William L. Westerman: professor of history at the universities of Wisconsin, Cornell, and Columbia; served as a trustee from 1921 until 1932; Professor in Charge of Classical Studies at the American Academy in Rome from 1926 to 1927, and a member of the Committee on the School of Classical Studies from 1922-1935.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
American Academy in Rome
Subjects-Topical:
Architecture -- Study and teaching; Architecture, Classical -- Study and teaching; Art -- Study and teaching; Art schools -- Italy -- Rome
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
Aldrich, Chester Holmes, 1871-1940; Boring, William, 1859-1937; Breck, George, 1863-1920; Dinsmoor, William B.; Egbert, J. C. (James Chidester), 1859-1948; Ely, Theo. N.; Faulkner, Barry, 1881-1966; Guernsey, Roscoe; Hewlett, James Monroe; Kendall, William M.; La Farge, C. Grant (Christopher Grant), 1862-1938; Marquand, Allan, 1853-1924; McKim, Charles Follen, 1847-1909; Mead, William Rutherford, 1846-1928; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912; Morey, Charles Rufus, 1877-1955; Mowbray, H. Siddons (Harry Siddons), 1858-1928; Platt, Charles A. (Charles Adams), 1861-1933; Pope, John Russell, 1874-1937; Roberts, Laurance P.; Smith, James Kellum, 1893-1963; Stevens, Gorham Phillips, b. 1876; Vedder, Elihu, 1836-1923; Vitale, Ferrucio, 1875-1933; Ward, John Quincy Adams, 1830-1910; American School of Architecture in Rome; American School of Classical Studies in Rome
Provenance
The academy donated the records of its predecessor institutions (American School of Architecture in Rome and American School of Classical Studies in Rome), selected Board of Trustees records, and New York office files to the Archives of American Art in 1982. An additional gift of Rome office records, including personal papers of director Gorham Phillips Stevens, was received in 1990. Prior to receiving these donations, the Archives of American Art borrowed printed matter of the academy, 1911-1964, for microfilming in 1965 (microfilm reels ITRO 2-3 and ITRO 11-13); very few of the items microfilmed in 1965 were among the records subsequently donated.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 5749-5800 and for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Predecessor Institutions, 1894-1913, Series 1:; (box 1; 0.88 linear ft.; Reels 5749-5750)
  This series is organized into two subseries.
  1.1: American School of Architecture in Rome, 1894-1898
  1.2: American School of Classical Studies in Rome, 1895-1913
  - American School of Architecture in Rome, 1894-1898, 1.1:
    The idea for a school for American artists in Europe was discussed by a group of architects, painters, and sculptors who met in Chicago while collaborating on the fine arts section of the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition. Its most enthusiastic proponent was architect Charles F. McKim who worked tirelessly to make the concept a reality. He was its main administrator, and often kept the school afloat financially with infusions of cash from his personal account. In 1897 it was decided to reorganize as an academy, and the American School of Architecture in Rome was legally dissolved and replaced by the American Academy in Rome.
    This subseries include records of the school's managing committee, correspondence, financial records, and printed matter. Among the managing committee's records are notes and correspondence relative to the founding of the institution; minute books which include a semi-annual report of the executive committee managing committee, copies of printed competition announcements, and an engrossed copy with a transcription of dissolution documents; and legal documents including records concerning the school's dissolution in 1898 prior to being reorganized as the American Academy in Rome, an 1895 certificate of the secretary to the bank, and the 1895 lease for the Villa Aurora. Correspondence is mostly that of Charles F. McKim (Vice President 1894-1895 and President 1895-1896) who handled administrative matters. Capital Stock Certificates, 1895, include an "Original Issues of Shares" list.
    - Managing Committee (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Organizational Meeting and Related Correspondence, undated, [1894]-1895 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Minute Books Vol. 1 (disbound), 1894-1897 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Minute Books Vol. 2, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Reports, 1895 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Legal Documents, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1894-1896 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Financial Records (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Capital Stock Certificates, 1895 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Invoices and Receipts, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Printed Matter, Scholarship Competition Announcements, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
  - American School of Classical Studies in Rome, 1895-1913, 1.2:
    The extant records of the American School of Classical Studies in Rome consist mainly of printed matter and financial records that were transferred to the Secretary of the American Academy in Rome by the Columbia-Knickerbocker Trust Co., New York. Other records related to the early history of the American School of Classical Studies in Rome are located in the archives of the Archaelogical Institute of America, Boston.
    This subseries includes records of the school's managing committee and of the committee on fellowships; publications; printed matter; and treasurers' records. The managing committee file consists of the preamble and proposed resolution concerning the school's merger with the American Academy in Rome. Annual reports of the medieval and renaissance studies committee includes extracts from the Bulletin of the Archaeological Institute of America and the Journal of the Archaeological Institute of America, fellowship applications, examination questions, and the proposed consolidation agreement. Treasurers' records include the files of Alex. Bell and Willard V. King. Bell's records are sparse and King's files, while more substantial than those that survive from Bell's tenure, are also incomplete.
    - Managing Committee, 1911 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Committee on Fellowships (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1900-1905 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Fellowship Applications (A-Z), 1903-1907 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Publications, Correspondence and Invoices re: Supplementary Papers of the Roman School, Volume I, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Printed Matter (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - General Information, undated, 1895-1898 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Notice of the Annual Meeting, Managing Committee, 1911 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Annual Reports of the Managing Committee and Director, 1901/02-1911/12 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Annual Reports of the Committee on Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1909/10-1911/12 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Fellowship Applications and Examination Questions, undated, 1895-1909 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Prospectuses, 1909/10-1912/13 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
      - Proposed Consolidation Agreement, 1911 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Treasurer's Records, Alex. Bell, Acting Treasurer, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Reel 5749)
    - Treasurer's Records, Willard V. King (Box 1, Reel 5749-5750)
      - Correspondence, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Reel 5749-5750)
      - Banking Records, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Budgets, Financial Statements, 1909-1913, undated (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Investments, 1910-1913 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Invoices, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Receipts for Salaries and Expenses, 1909-1913 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
- Board of Trustees Records, 1897-1957, undated, Series 2:; (box 1-17; 15.32 linear ft.)
  From its earliest days, the American Academy in Rome has included architects, painters, and sculptors among its Trustees. After its merger with the American School of Classical Studies in Rome, classical scholars and archaeologists were added.
  Records maintained by the Board of Trustees are arranged into three subseries.
  2.1: Legal Documents, Minutes and Reports of Trustees, 1897-1946
  2.2: Board of Trustees Committee Minutes, 1905-1946, undated
  2.3: Records of Officers, 1897-1957, undated
  - Legal Documents, Minutes and Reports of Trustees, 1897-1946, 2.1:
    Minutes and reports of the Board of Trustees, including those of its annual meetings, are carbon copies rather than the official minute books, and are incomplete. Reports of officers are also incomplete. Included here are reports of officers' and trustees' visits to Rome, as well as reports of the Director and Secretary in Rome submitted to the Board of Trustees. The 1913 Director's report includes reports of the Director of the School of Fine Arts, the Director of the School of Classical Studies, and the Librarian.
    - Legal Documents (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - By-Laws and Amendments, undated, 1905-1926 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Certificate of Incorporation, 1897 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Constitution and Amendments, undated, 1897, 1901 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
    - Minutes, 1897-1947, 1957 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
    - Reports (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - President, 1898, 1909 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Secretary, 1907 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Treasurer, 1911-1934/35 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Officers'/Trustees' Visits to Rome, 1908-1939 (Box 1, Reel 5750)
      - Director (Rome), 1908-1938; 1946 (Box 2, Reel 5750-5751)